Alright let&#39;s have a look at some basic select queries and then
understand how this works. I&#39;m in SQL Server Management Studio and
I&#39;ve connected to my Azure SQL Database. And what I&#39;m going to do is I&#39;m going to
create a new query,
I&#39;m clicking the New Query button. And I get this window appearing here
into which I can start typing my Transact-SQL. Now before I type
any Transact-SQL code,
I just want to notice which database I&#39;m in. We talk about the database context
as being
the database the you&#39;re currently working in or that you&#39;re currently connected
to.
And you can see that by default it is connected me to a database called master
which is a system database this used internally by the system.
I actually want to be working in the AdventureWorks database or the
AdventureWorksLT
database. So I&#39;ll go ahead and select that.
And I&#39;ll guarantee you, when you&#39;re working on the labs at some point you&#39;ll find
yourself in the wrong database and you&#39;ll get an error that says
an object couldn&#39;t be found or something like that. Just double check that
you&#39;re working in the right database,
as a little tip. So know that I&#39;m there, I&#39;m going to
go ahead and start executing some Transact-SQL. So I&#39;ll use my SELECT statement
and I&#39;ll just a go with every programmers friend
the first program everybody ever writes. Here&#39;s the Transact-SQL version of Hello World
or hello Graeme in this case. If I select that, back it comes. It&#39;s one column
and it&#39;s got the
the literal string that I typed in there. So
it&#39;s not particularly very useful but it does at least show me that might my SELECT
statement is working, it&#39;s bringing back that literal value.
What I probably want to do though is to get some data from
some tables in the database. So I&#39;m going to SELECT *
FROM SalesLT.Product
Now let&#39;s just take a look at that for a second.
SalesLT is the schema. You might remember we talked about tables belonging
to a schema.
And Product is the name of the table. And the SELECT * means
bring back all the columns. I&#39;m not specific about which columns I want,
I want to see all the columns in this table.
And I&#39;ll go ahead and I&#39;ll execute that code.
And sure enough it brings back a huge big results set with
data for all the columns that are in that table. So
I&#39;ve got 295 rows there. I can see down here in the corner
and I&#39;ve got all these columns across here including columns that I probably
don&#39;t really need. I won&#39;t really need that rowguid column or the
ThumbnailPhotoFileName or any of these kind of things as I&#39;m working with it.
So that brings us to our first kind of best practice when you&#39;re working with
Transact-SQL
and that is only bring back what you need. Try and avoid using SELECT *
and explicitly saying which
of the columns you&#39;re interested in. So in this case, I&#39;m interested and
ProductID, the Name, the
ListPrice, and the StandardCost.
Now, I could leave all that on one line like that,
it doesn&#39;t really make any difference if you put a new line. I could
put a whole bunch of new lines in there or
space it out anyway I like. The
indicator that the end of the statement has been reached is this
semi-colon at the end. And now technically that&#39;s optional
in the current releases of SQL Server and Azure SQL Database
but is good practice to put a semi-colon at the end of the statement just to
be clear about that defines the entire statement that I want to
run.
So if I go ahead and Execute that,
I get back those four columns that I specified. I get back
my ID, my name, my ListPrice, and my StandardCosts.
So far so good. Now what I might also want to do is I might want to bring
back
the ListPrice minus the StandardCost.
So it&#39;s not a column, it&#39;s an expression. It&#39;s
a calculation that I want the the system to perform for me.
So if I go ahead and and run that, it works. It brings back the
ListPrice minus the StandardCosts, so I can see that there.
But of course there&#39;s no column name here because it doesn&#39;t know what to call that column.
It&#39;s not defined in the table,
so it doesn&#39;t have a name. So what we&#39;ll want to do is actually give it some sort
of meaningful name.
And I do that by saying as and then the name I want to assign to it.
And sure enough it now comes back as a column
named Margin which is pretty useful. Now there is an alternative syntax that I could use. You don&#39;t
actually have to use as.
If I omit the as, it will still work if I go ahead and run that
it still comes by being called Margin. So
you don&#39;t need the as. And if you&#39;re particularly lazy you might think that&#39;s
fine, that&#39;ll save me typing two characters, I won&#39;t bother
having that. The problem is it&#39;s very easy
to type a query perhaps you know in this case I want the color
to come back. But I&#39;ve forgotton to type in a comma
to separate that out. And if I do that, what I actually get in this case is the ListPrice
minus the StandardCost
in a column called Color which doesn&#39;t make any sense whatsoever. And it&#39;s
because I forgot to put in that
missing comma. That&#39;s not actually what I wanted.
So my second tip is
make sure you always use the as
keyword when you&#39;re assigning an alias to a column so that we know that we&#39;re
getting the
the proper name. And you can assign aliases to any column. It doesn&#39;t have to be
ones that have got expressions, if I just want to call StandardCost
Cost I could do that as well. And you can see that it works. So these aliases, they&#39;re just ways of
renaming columns
or assigning names to columns that are defined by
calculations or  expressions that that wouldn&#39;t otherwise have a name.
Okay so we&#39;re getting some data out of here. We&#39;re seeing some of the
syntax and tricks that we can use with it.
And let&#39;s explore a little bit more this idea using expressions. And we&#39;ve
seen
we did ListPrice minus StandardCost. Now let&#39;s try something else. Let&#39;s
get rid of our costs and our prices and start to think about the color
and also the size. So we can start off by looking at the ProductID, the Name, the
Color, and the Size.
And you can see that the colors are as you would expect different
colors. The sizes are some of them are numbers
some of them are letters or character data, and some of them are null. So some
of the sizes are unknown or are not relevant or
or just missing. So what happens if
I tell it that I want Color
plus Size. So let&#39;s
go-ahead run that. And I get no column name as you would expect.
But I do actually get something happening here. I get Black58,
to the color was Black, the size was 58 and this
has been evaluated to be Black58. So it&#39;s not trying to
add things together as you might expect with the plus sign. Because these are
both
character columns, these are both strings, what it&#39;s doing is it&#39;s concatenating them.
So I could give that a name, called as Style,
and that&#39;s perhaps some way as defining my style as being some combination of the
the color and size. But you&#39;ll notice that
where the size is null, what I don&#39;t get, I might expect to get
you know Red with without any size here. But I actually get null.
And that&#39;s because of the way that nulls behave. Null means
unknown. Null means I don&#39;t know what the value is here. So
Red plus something I don&#39;t know
equals something that I don&#39;t know. It&#39;s an unknown answer.
So what we get is a null. It doesn&#39;t treat a null as being a blank
string or empty column. It treats it as being
unknown value. So when you add, or you
subtract, or you do any sort of a calculation or any sort of expression
that uses a null, it
usually then evaluates to null if any one of the two things that
you working with is a null.
So that&#39;s worth being aware of as well. And then one final thing that&#39;s worth being aware
as well, I&#39;ve got the color and the size and some of the sizes are in fact
numbers.
So you might think that it&#39;s possible to do
something like this. It doesn&#39;t make much sense, but I might say
show me the ListPrice plus the Size.
And let&#39;s see what&#39;s going to happen there. And what&#39;s actually going to happen there is that I&#39;m
going to get an error.
And the error is well, I can&#39;t do that because you&#39;re trying to do an operation
has a numerical value in the ListPrice
and a text value in the size column. So
it doesn&#39;t add it together where it is a number. It just says no these these two things
are incompatible, you can&#39;t
do that. You can&#39;t add a number to a  string. I don&#39;t know what it is you want
to try and do here
so I&#39;m going to give you an error that says I can&#39;t convert it to the appropriate
data type. It&#39;s actually a money data type, the ListPrice. So
we&#39;ve seen some examples of how to use Transact-SQL, and how to create some queries
and we&#39;ve also set ourselves up to look at some the
potential pitfalls, potential little problems that we might run across
which we&#39;ll explore in some of the later demos.